Do you know when disasters first became a subject of scientific research?
大家知道災害是從什麼時候開始成為科學研究對象的嗎？
A major turning point was the Great Lisbon Earthquake that occurred on November 1, 1755
一個重大的轉捩點，就是1755年11月1日發生的里斯本大地震
About 270 years ago in Europe, earthquakes were believed to be the wrath of God
大約270年前的歐洲，人們認為地震是上帝的憤怒
The Great Lisbon Earthquake became a major catalyst for changing that belief
里斯本大地震成為改變這種觀念的重要契機
It not only made earthquakes a subject of scientific study
它不僅使地震成為科學研究的對象
but also fundamentally transformed the way scientific research itself was conducted
更從根本上改變了科學研究本身的方式
Today, let's trace how disasters once thought to be divine wrath
今天，讓我們追溯曾被認為是神怒的災害
became subjects of scientific inquiry
是如何轉變為科學探究的對象
and explore this historical journey
一起來探索這段歷史吧
First, let's look at the scale of the Great Lisbon Earthquake
首先，讓我們來看看里斯本大地震的規模有多大
It occurred on November 1, 1755, around 9:40 AM
發生時間是1755年11月1日上午9點40分左右
The epicenter was about 220 km off Cape St. Vincent in the Atlantic Ocean
震央位於大西洋聖文森特角外海約220公里處
The estimated magnitude was between 8.5 and 9
推估規模為8.5到9級
Similar to or even larger than the 2011 Great East Japan Earthquake
與2011年東日本大地震相當，甚至更大
This earthquake destroyed approximately 85% of the buildings in Lisbon
這場地震摧毀了里斯本市內約85%的建築物
and the death toll is estimated to have reached 30,000 to 40,000 people
死亡人數估計達到3萬至4萬人
What was particularly terrifying was the triple disaster
特別可怕的是三重災害
First, building collapses from three major tremors
首先是三次大震動造成的建築物倒塌
Then, a massive tsunami that struck after the sea first receded
接著是海水退去後襲來的巨大海嘯
And fires that broke out throughout the city from overturned cooking equipment
然後是烹飪器具傾倒等原因在市內各處引發的火災
Contemporary copper engravings show the devastating scale of the destruction
從當時的銅版畫可以看出災害的慘烈程度
Moreover, the tsunami reached as far as the Azores and the West Indies
而且這次地震的海嘯甚至到達了亞速爾群島和西印度群島
and tremors were observed throughout Europe
整個歐洲都觀測到了震動
This was a widespread disaster that caused massive damage across all of Europe and the Atlantic
這是一場波及全歐洲和整個大西洋的大規模災害
So why did this earthquake become such a special turning point in the history of science?
那麼，為什麼這場地震在科學史上成為如此特殊的轉捩點呢？
It is deeply related to the timing and location of this earthquake
這與地震發生的時機和地點密切相關
November 1st was All Saints' Day, an important Catholic holiday
11月1日是萬聖節，天主教的重要節日
Devout citizens were attending Mass in churches
虔誠的市民們正在教堂參加彌撒
when the earthquake struck at that very moment
地震就在那一刻襲來
While churches collapsed and many believers perished
教堂倒塌，許多信徒罹難
brothels and similar establishments remained unscathed, and people began to question
而妓院等場所卻毫髮無傷，人們開始質疑
"Why did God destroy a city of good citizens?"
「為什麼上帝要摧毀善良市民的城市？」
To draw a Japanese analogy, it would be like shrines and temples being destroyed
用日本來比喻的話，就像神社和寺廟被摧毀了
while the flashy entertainment district buildings remained intact
而華麗的風化區建築卻安然無恙
Here, two interpretations came into conflict
在這裡，兩種解釋產生了對立
One was the traditional divine punishment theory
一種是傳統的天譴說
The interpretation that it was God's wrath against the citizens' sins
認為這是上帝對市民罪行的憤怒
The other was a new approach: exploring it scientifically as a natural phenomenon
另一種是將其作為自然現象進行科學探究的新方法
This conflict became the starting point for historically viewing earthquakes as natural disasters from a scientific perspective
這種對立正是從科學角度看待地震這一自然災害的歷史轉變的起點
Actually, even before the Great Lisbon Earthquake
其實，在里斯本大地震發生之前
a culture of scientific observation was already developing in Europe
歐洲就已經在培養科學觀察的文化
In 1660, the Royal Society of London was established
1660年，英國皇家學會成立
Its motto was "Nullius in verba"
其座右銘是「Nullius in verba」
meaning "Take nobody's word for it"
意思是「不盲從權威」
In other words, not "because the Bible says so"
也就是說，不是「因為聖經這麼說」
or "because the Church says so"
或「因為教會這麼說」
but rather observe directly, gather data, and think for yourself
而是實際觀察、收集數據、獨立思考
In 1665, the scientific journal Philosophical Transactions was launched
1665年，科學期刊《自然哲學會刊》創刊
and earthquake reports began to accumulate
地震報告開始累積
In the approximately 90 years before the Great Lisbon Earthquake, about 70 observational records were collected
在里斯本大地震之前的約90年間，收集了約70份觀測記錄
Particularly important was the London earthquake of 1750
特別重要的是1750年的倫敦地震
Many reports were made about this earthquake
這次地震產生了許多報告
and an interesting observation was made here
在這裡進行了一項有趣的觀察
It was the concept of "earthquake trajectory"
那就是「地震軌跡」的概念
The arrival time and intensity of shaking varied by location
震動的到達時間和強度因地點而異
In other words, the recognition emerged that "earthquakes are moving phenomena"
也就是說，「地震是移動現象」這一認識誕生了
This was the starting point for our modern understanding of seismic wave propagation from the epicenter
這成為我們現代理解地震波從震央傳播的起點
So by the time the Great Lisbon Earthquake occurred
也就是說，到里斯本大地震發生時
there was already nearly a century of accumulated observational records
已經有了近一個世紀的觀測記錄積累
and the seeds of a scientific methodology for interpreting earthquakes scientifically had sprouted
科學解釋地震的科學方法的萌芽已經出現
So far, we've looked at the preparatory period before the Great Lisbon Earthquake
到目前為止，我們看了里斯本大地震之前的準備期
The accumulation of observational records, the empirical rule that earthquakes are moving phenomena
觀測記錄的積累、地震是移動現象的經驗法則
These formed the foundation that made scientific investigation after the disaster possible
這些形成了災後科學調查得以進行的基礎
Now, let's look at how people actually reacted
接下來，讓我們看看大地震發生時
when the great earthquake occurred
人們實際上是如何反應的
Now, when the Great Lisbon Earthquake struck
那麼，當里斯本大地震發生時
two people showed contrasting reactions
有兩個人表現出了截然不同的反應
One was the Jesuit missionary Gabriel Malagrida
一位是耶穌會傳教士加布里埃爾·馬拉格里達
He preached that "This is divine punishment for the sins of the citizens"
他宣稱「這是上帝對市民罪行的懲罰」
The other was the Portuguese Prime Minister, the Marquis of Pombal, Carvalho
另一位是葡萄牙首相龐巴爾侯爵卡瓦略
He took an entirely different approach
他採取了完全不同的方法
Carvalho conducted a scientific questionnaire survey
卡瓦略進行了科學問卷調查
The questions were something like this:
問題內容大概是這樣的：
"What time did the earthquake start and how long did it last?"
「地震是什麼時候開始的，持續了多久？」
"Did the sea recede or rise?"
「海水是退了還是漲了？」
"How high was it?"
「高度有多少？」
"Was there a directional pattern to building collapses?"
「建築物倒塌有方向性嗎？」
In other words, instead of asking "Why did God cause such a disaster?"
也就是說，他問的不是「為什麼上帝要造成這樣的災害？」
he asked "How did the earthquake occur?"
而是「地震是如何發生的？」
and "What kind of damage resulted from the earthquake?"
「地震造成了什麼樣的損害？」
This difference illustrates the essence of scientific inquiry
這種差異展示了科學探究的本質
While theological interpretation asks "Why did God cause this?"
神學解釋問的是「為什麼上帝造成這件事？」
the scientific approach seeks to clarify how it happened
而科學方法則試圖釐清事情是如何發生的
Furthermore, when rebuilding Lisbon, Carvalho adopted the earthquake-resistant Gaiola structure
此外，卡瓦略在重建里斯本時採用了抗震的籠屋結構
and reportedly had soldiers march to make buildings vibrate as an empirical test
據說還讓士兵行軍使建築物振動，進行實證實驗
This is considered one of the earliest examples of applying experimental scientific methods to disaster preparedness
這被認為是將實驗科學方法應用於防災的最早期案例之一
News of the Great Lisbon Earthquake spread throughout Europe, and many intellectuals responded
里斯本大地震的消息傳遍了整個歐洲，許多知識分子做出了回應
One of them was the famous philosopher Immanuel Kant
其中之一就是著名哲學家伊曼努爾·康德
In 1756, Kant published three papers in quick succession
1756年，康德在短時間內發表了三篇論文
Kant's argument was clear
康德的論點很明確
"Earthquakes are purely physical and chemical phenomena"
「地震純粹是物理和化學現象」
He proposed a hypothesis that earthquakes were caused by underground combustion of sulfur and iron
他提出了地震是由地下硫磺和鐵燃燒引起的假說
From the perspective of modern seismology, this hypothesis has been disproven
從現代地震學的角度來看，這個假說已被否定
However, what was important was the attempt to understand earthquake mechanisms as scientific phenomena
然而，重要的是試圖將地震機制作為科學現象來理解
Kant said:
康德說：
"Earthquakes are not divine punishment"
「地震不是天譴」
"They are merely natural phenomena"
「它只是自然現象」
"They are necessary phenomena following natural laws and have no moral meaning"
「它是遵循自然法則的必然現象，沒有道德意義」
This was a revolutionary claim for its time
這是完全排斥神學解釋的
completely rejecting theological interpretation
在當時是革命性的主張
Then a person who made important contributions to the development of seismology appeared
然後，一位對地震學發展做出重要貢獻的人物出現了
The English physicist John Michell
英國物理學家約翰·米歇爾
In 1759, Michell submitted a paper on earthquakes to the Royal Society
1759年，米歇爾向英國皇家學會提交了一篇關於地震的論文
and was elected a Fellow in 1760
並於1760年當選為會員
This paper is recognized as a pioneering work in seismology
這篇論文被認為是地震學的先驅之作
and is still highly regarded today
至今仍受到高度評價
Michell's contributions were groundbreaking
米歇爾的貢獻是開創性的
He theorized that earthquakes propagate as waves
他認為地震是以波的形式傳播的現象
This was one of the earliest theories to conceptualize earthquakes as waves
這是最早將地震概念化為波的理論之一
He also proposed a geometric approach to estimate where earthquakes occurred
他還提出了用幾何方法估計地震發生位置的方法
what we now call determining the epicenter
也就是我們現在所說的確定震央
Furthermore, he estimated the propagation speed of earthquakes at about 530 m/s
此外，他估計地震的傳播速度約為530公尺/秒
We now know that seismic waves (P-waves) travel at 5-8 km/s
我們現在知道地震波（P波）的速度是5-8公里/秒
but this was a revolutionary attempt for its time
但這在當時是革命性的嘗試
Michell also pointed out that tsunamis are caused by submarine earthquakes
米歇爾還指出海嘯是由海底地震引起的
and that geological faulting is related to earthquakes
以及地層錯動與地震有關
These insights were extremely important contributions to understanding earthquakes scientifically
這些見解對於科學理解地震極為重要
What enabled Michell to make these scientific observations?
是什麼使米歇爾能夠做出這些科學觀察呢？
It was the power of data
是數據的力量
The empirical rule from the 1750 London earthquake that earthquakes are moving phenomena
1750年倫敦地震得出的地震是移動現象的經驗法則
Carvalho's systematic questionnaire survey
卡瓦略的系統性問卷調查
Based on this data, Michell was able to accurately estimate
基於這些數據，米歇爾能夠準確估計
the epicenter of the Great Lisbon Earthquake as being in the Atlantic Ocean
里斯本大地震的震央位於大西洋
Here we see the beginning of data-based scientific earthquake research
這裡是基於數據的科學地震研究的開端
Now, let's move to the mid-19th century
現在，讓我們進入19世紀中葉
Here we meet Robert Mallet, known as "the father of seismology"
在這裡我們遇到了被稱為「地震學之父」的羅伯特·馬萊
Mallet studied earthquakes through an experimental approach
馬萊用實驗方法研究地震
In 1849, Mallet buried explosives underground and conducted blast experiments
1849年，馬萊在地下埋設炸藥進行爆破實驗
He measured the speed of seismic waves at a location about 800 meters away
他在約800公尺外的地方測量地震波的速度
About 251 m/s in wet sand
在濕沙中約251公尺/秒
About 427 m/s in granite
在花崗岩中約427公尺/秒
In other words, he demonstrated that propagation speed varies depending on the medium
也就是說，他證明了傳播速度因介質而異
This was a very important discovery for understanding the properties of seismic waves
這對於理解地震波的性質是非常重要的發現
And in 1858, Mallet created a world seismic distribution map
1858年，馬萊製作了世界地震分布圖
He catalogued about 6,800 historical earthquakes and showed that earthquakes occur predominantly in specific regions
他將約6800次歷史地震編目，並顯示地震主要發生在特定地區
Remarkably, this distribution closely matches the plate boundaries we know today
令人驚訝的是，這種分布與我們今天所知的板塊邊界幾乎一致
The scientific inquiry that began with the 1755 Great Lisbon Earthquake
從1755年里斯本大地震開始的科學探究
through the contributions of scientists like Kant, Michell, and Mallet
經過康德、米歇爾、馬萊等科學家的貢獻
can be said to have established seismology as an academic discipline over about 100 years
可以說在約100年間確立了地震學這門學科
And this scientific knowledge is now being used for modern disaster prevention and mitigation
而這些科學知識現在正被用於現代防災和減災
Earthquake early warning systems, earthquake-resistant construction, tsunami warning systems
地震預警系統、耐震建築、海嘯警報系統
All of these can be said to be extensions of the scientific inquiry
所有這些都可以說是250多年前
that began in Lisbon over 250 years ago
在里斯本開始的科學探究的延伸
On November 1, 1755, the great earthquake that struck Lisbon
1755年11月1日，襲擊里斯本的大地震
became a major catalyst for making disasters subjects of natural science research
成為使災害成為自然科學研究對象的重要契機
And today, that scientific knowledge
而今天，這些科學知識
is being applied to disaster prevention and mitigation technologies that protect our lives
正被應用於保護我們生命的防災和減災技術
I hope you've gained a sense of how history connects to our lives today
希望大家能感受到歷史與我們今天生活的聯繫
Until next time, take care!
那麼下次再見，再會！